History is often presented [music] as a
set of facts and dates,
of victories and defeats,
of monarchs and presidents,
all consigned to an unchanging past.
>> [screaming]
>> BUT IT'S NOT LIKE THAT AT ALL.
>> [music]
>> History is the knitting together of
rival interpretations,
deliberate manipulations of the truth,
and sometimes
alternative facts.
In this series, I'll be lifting the lid
on three of American history's greatest
national stories.
The Civil War.
Was it really a battle to reunite the
nation and liberate the slaves in the
South?
The Cold War supremacy,
American dream
or nuclear nightmare?
And in this [music] program, the
American Revolution.
How a British colony
won its freedom from the biggest empire
[music] in the world.
This is the story of the birth of the
United States. It's a tale of David and
Goliath with high ideals and heroism and
the ringing of the Liberty Bell.
It's a story [music] that continues to
inspire in politics, literature, and
even on Broadway. But how [music] much
of America's founding story is founded
on fact? Did the Liberty Bell really
ring out on July [music] the 4th, 1776?
Who really won the War of Independence?
American rebels or the King of France?
>> The Americans could never have uh
brought themselves up by their own
bootstraps.
>> And was George Washington a man who
truly believed in liberty and equality?
>> It shakes the very foundation of
American history.
>> Generations of politicians and poets and
protesters have used the story of the
American Revolution.
Sometimes to unite the American people,
sometimes to divide them.
And the story they've told often
supersizes the truth
and comes with a side order of fibs.
>> [music]
>> Early in July 1776,
a future [music] American president
wrote a letter to his wife.
He was a leader in the American
Revolution.
And the previous day, the United States
had declared its independence from Great
Britain.
>> John Adams [music] knew that this day
would be celebrated for generations to
come. He said that it ought to be
solemnized with pomp and PARADES
AND GAMES
AND GUNS
AND BONFIRES
and illuminations
from one end of America to the other.
The 2nd of July, he said, would become
the most memorable day in American
history. And he was very nearly right.
>> [music]
[music]
>> But the 2nd of July, of course, was soon
forgotten.
The wording of the Declaration of
Independence wasn't finally approved
until two days later.
>> Happy 4th of July!
>> [music]
>> The British Empire's first American
colony was founded in Virginia in 1607.
By 1732,
Britain had 13 colonies along the
Atlantic coast.
But in the 1760s,
American rebels rose up against British
taxes.
They called themselves patriots, and
after eight years of war, a plucky army
of rebel farmers won its revolt against
the British Empire.
Heroic General George Washington became
the first president of the land of the
free, a nation promising liberty and
equality to all.
This version of the story is central to
America's national identity,
and it's given the American people a
sense of special destiny that their
country is going to lead the rest of the
world to freedom.
But just as with any type of history,
the line between fact and fiction is
blurred.
The American Revolution, so the story
goes, started with a tea party.
In December [music] 1773,
three British-owned ships sat in Boston
Harbor, laden with tea.
But the people of Boston wouldn't let
them unload their cargo.
Because that tea came with a British
tax, levied by a parliament in London,
where Americans had no votes and no
voice.
The disgruntled American colonists
wanted to send the British a clear
message. No taxation without
representation.
So one night, they dressed up as Mohawk
Indians. They came storming onto the
ships. They cracked open the crates,
then they threw the tea.
Right into Boston Harbor. Yes.
This has been celebrated in history as a
jolly jape in fancy dress, a glorious
stunt that sparked [screaming] a
revolution.
But the protest came after years of dark
and bloody violence between American
colonists and British troops in the
city.
And the rebels were disguised as Mohawk
Indians to avoid arrest.
This wasn't called a tea party at the
time. Many in America saw it as a crime.
Now some influential people, people like
Benjamin Franklin and George Washington,
thought that the destruction of the tea
was a bad idea. Destroying private
property,
that could even damage their cause.
>> [music]
>> The Mohawk stunt also allowed the
British to condemn the American
colonists as a criminal mob.
So the destruction of the tea was
originally a violent, aggressive,
illegal action. When did it become this
sort of cuddly tea party?
>> Well, it became known as the tea party
about 50 years after the event in the
mid-1820s.
And that was at the time when a lot of
those who took part in the tea party
were beginning to die off. So, there was
an attempt then, beginning around that
time, to reflect back on that act and it
was not thought of as
an act of destruction, but rather
something that was more patriotic and
that had become sort of a cornerstone of
the of the revolution itself.
One of the people who
remembered the event, although he
reportedly was only about 5 years old at
the time,
um
gave this vial of tea in 1840, gave it
to to this institution. And so, this tea
says, "Tea thrown into the Boston
Harbor, December 16, 1773."
>> Do you believe it's the tea? I'm
doubtful this is the tea.
>> Well, you should be doubtful, but I
think it's possible.
>> And the point is that in 1840, when he
gave it to this museum, he was wanting
to remember
>> Exactly.
>> this cornerstone of American history and
memory itself.
>> real or not doesn't really matter.
>> It doesn't, does it? It's just the story
that's told.
>> It was all part of this renewal and
revival of this [music] event that by
this time much of the violence
associated with it was forgotten.
>> The story [music] of the tea party takes
on a new meaning with each retelling.
In the 19th century, it became patriotic
fun with dressing up.
In the 1970s, it was used to support
calls for Richard Nixon to be impeached.
And in the 21st century, it's been
adopted by the radical right's tea party
movement.
>> We are going to make America great
again. Thank you. Thank you very much.
>> [applause]
[cheering]
>> Back in the 18th century, the tea party
provokes a dramatic response from the
British.
In 1774,
George the third and the British
Parliament punished Boston.
Political meetings were shut down
and the port was closed.
Tensions mounted.
In 1775, [music]
the rebels were stockpiling guns and
ammunition. They were getting ready for
war. But the British, well, on to them.
British troops were ordered to go to
seize and destroy weapons that were
being stored in the Massachusetts towns
of Lexington and Concord.
The American [music] patriots got wind
of the British plan. So, they set up a
signaling system.
When the British mobilized, lanterns
would appear in the tower at the North
Church [music]
here in Boston.
One lantern meant that the British were
marching to Concord.
Two meant that they were traveling by
[music] boat.
At the signal, a patriot would ride
through the countryside to alert the
local militia.
Paul Revere was a local craftsman.
That night, he would become a folk hero.
Paul Revere is celebrated as the single
courageous hero who rode through the
night to warn the Americans that the
British were coming.
But this is actually something of a fib.
And [music] it was all cooked up by one
of America's greatest poets.
In 1860, 85 years after the event, Henry
Wadsworth Longfellow wrote a stirring
poem about Revere's ride.
It's been learned by generations [music]
of American school kids.
>> [music]
>> Listen, my children, and you shall hear
of the midnight ride of Paul Revere.
[music]
>> But the poem isn't the only version of
the story.
Revere himself described [music] his
ride in a statement made soon after the
event.
He then wrote a more elaborate version
23 [music]
years later.
In each retelling of the story, though,
events become more dramatic, and Revere
takes a different route.
In the poem, Revere sees the signal in
the church tower and sets off, a lone
rider in the moonlit night.
The fate [music] of history is in one
man's hands.
But according to Revere's own account,
there's a second rider, Mr. Dawes.
Revere rode north of the British route
to avoid discovery, while Dawes rode to
the south of it.
After stopping at Lexington to warn
rebel leaders, they then headed towards
Concord with a third man.
But poetry prefers a solitary hero,
David taking on Goliath.
>> Longfellow's poem takes Paul Revere, the
lone hero, step by step through the
Massachusetts countryside. By 1:00 a.m.,
he reaches Lexington. [music]
2:00 a.m., he gets to Concord. Hooray!
He's in time to wake the sleeping
locals. Mission accomplished.
Now, here's a funny
If you look at Revere's own accounts,
this is one of them, you discover that
he never actually made it to Concord
that night because after leaving
Lexington, he was captured by [music]
the British.
>> In reality, it was the third rider who
warned Concord that the British were on
the march.
But Longfellow's poetic version
guaranteed a place in history for Paul
Revere.
The morning after Revere's ride, the
local militia in Lexington were ready
and waiting for the British.
But the British army overwhelmed the
rebels.
A company of British soldiers then
marched to the bridge in the neighboring
town of Concord.
>> By the time the British got to the
bridge, there were 500 militiamen
waiting for them on this side and battle
broke out. The British had only sent 100
soldiers.
They were pretty soon outnumbered,
overpowered, and they began to retreat
back towards Boston.
>> 73 British soldiers were killed in
Lexington and Concord and 50 Americans.
At the battlefield in Concord is a
memorial to the American [music]
colonists who fought here.
These men were not professional
soldiers. They were the local militia.
In the colonies, all men were trained to
fight with their own muskets to protect
their communities in an emergency.
>> This statue celebrates the militiaman as
ordinary farmers. He's just a regular
bloke, if implausibly handsome. The
statue was put up 100 years after the
battle.
And you can tell he's ordinary because
he's not wearing a military uniform. And
although he's carrying a musket, he's
brought his plow with him, too.
At the foot of the statue are lines of
verse from the Concord Hymn, written by
the poet Ralph Waldo Emerson in 1837.
The poem talks about the patriots as the
embattled farmers who fired the shot
heard round the world.
These are the little people taking on
the forces of history. They're amateurs
taking on the professional British Army.
Once again, it's David and Goliath.
This image of brave farmers taking up
arms to beat the British has become a
central part of the powerful mythology
of the American Revolution.
But it's a distorted version of what
really happened.
So, these amateur soldiers, were they
the men who really um defeated the
British? That's what we're supposed to
think, isn't it?
>> That is the ideal. That's why we have
the statue of somebody going back to his
plow. But in fact, the American leaders
knew that they couldn't do that with
just militia troops. So, they needed a
professional army, what became the
Continental Army, to win the war.
>> Three months after Lexington and
Concord, Congress created the
Continental Army. At first, it united
the local militias from across the
colonies.
>> Take aim.
>> But under General George Washington, it
started recruiting and training as a
professional army.
>> March.
>> So, this Continental Army, this proper
army, it won the war. What happens next?
>> Uh there was great rejoicing. Everybody
uh was celebrated the victory, and then
the army disbanded.
This was because uh the United States
felt it was safe now that Britain was
recognizing its independence, and
because they did not want the expense or
the possible danger of professional uh
forces hanging around.
>> What's the danger that that had to keep
us safe on this?
>> Tyranny. Uh the possibility of a
military dictator or an oligarchy of
rich men taking over our fine fragile
republic. That's the idea.
>> At the end of the war, even General
George Washington resigned his post and
returned to his farm in Virginia.
The new nation would have no major
professional army, but men would
continue to bear [music] arms and serve
in the local militia.
>> They felt that the ideal citizen was
somebody who had uh land, and family,
and business, and was rooted in a
community, and not one of these restless
soldiers obeying orders from some higher
power.
>> So, [music] your ideal citizen owns his
own gun?
>> At that time, yes. To be a fully uh a
member of the community in its
self-defense, you needed to be part of
the militia, and that usually meant
having your own musket.
>> This belief that the founders [music]
had in their citizen soldiers was so
important, it got enshrined in the new
nation's Bill of Rights.
The Second Amendment says that having a
militia is absolutely necessary for
security.
And it says that the people's right to
bear arms shall not be infringed.
This statement still forms the basis of
US gun law to this day.
Almost as if Americans are still living
in the 18th century.
And to me, the irony is that it wasn't
even these normal blokes with guns who
defeated the British anyway.
At Lexington [music] and Concord, the
first shots of war were fired.
But this wasn't yet a revolution to
topple a king.
So now, a new battle began over how to
use the story of the conflict to win
support from King George the third.
Each side produced conflicting
eyewitness accounts.
>> The British claimed that they weren't
looking for a fight. They just wanted to
capture those military supplies. They
said that the American rebels fired
first, so they were only acting in
self-defense. Also, the Americans abused
the dead. They cut off their scalps.
But the Americans said the British
started it. They attacked unprovoked.
Also, they were thirsty for blood. The
British are supposed to have chucked
pregnant women out of their beds and
killed unarmed people in their own
homes.
>> Whatever really happened, American
patriots hoped that George the third
would intervene when he understood the
injustice against his colonial subjects.
The patriots chartered a fast ship to
take their version of events to England.
It arrived two weeks before the British
army's own account.
In mid-1775,
the majority in America was still
opposed to independence.
Their beef was with Parliament. They
remained loyal to George the third.
But radicals, inspired by enlightenment
thinking, wanted a revolution.
And they could only justify this if the
king was seen as a tyrant acting against
the interests of the people.
>> If America was going to make a go of it
as an independent nation, then the
Patriot leaders needed to convince the
people that George the third was a cruel
tyrant.
>> In the 1760s, [music]
the king had been celebrated for
defending the colonists against
Parliament.
>> [music]
>> As recently as 1770, a statue to George
the third had been put up here in New
York's Bowling Green Park.
But in 1775,
further bloodshed in Boston convinced
King George of the Americans [music]
treachery.
>> In August 1775,
George the third proclaimed that his
American subjects were now definitely in
a state of open rebellion and that his
troops must do their utmost to put it
down.
Now to the Americans who still saw
themselves as loyal to George the third,
this was a terrible blow. Their king had
just turned them into traitors.
>> At the [music] opening of the British
Parliament in October 1775,
the king repeated his accusations of
rebellion.
And when the news reached America, a
piece of propaganda was about to make
the [music] king look even worse.
>> This is the Pennsylvania Evening Post
[music] for the 9th of January, 1776.
This edition contains the whole of the
king's speech. It goes on for quite some
time.
It finishes here on page 15 and down
here is an advert for a new pamphlet to
be published on the very same day. The
topic is the tyranny of the monarchy.
The title of the pamphlet is Common
Sense and the author is Thomas Paine.
>> Thomas Paine was a British-born radical
who became a leading voice in both the
American and French Revolutions.
He believed independence was the answer
to America's problems.
Common Sense was his argument for a
revolution.
>> Now, Thomas Paine was really brilliant
at using simple, persuasive language
that appealed to a mass audience. And
Common Sense became an almost instant
best-seller.
In it, he never directly named King
George the III, but by implication, he
was pretty rude about him.
Paine talks about the Pharaoh of England
and the royal brute.
He was casting George the III as the
villain of this story.
>> Within 6 months of the publication of
Common Sense, in July 1776,
the United States denounced the monarch
and proclaimed itself an independent
nation. [music]
America's Declaration of Independence is
remembered for its high ideals of
liberty [music] and equality. But that's
just one line.
The bulk of the document was a tirade of
grievances
against [music] a tyrannous King George.
>> After a public reading of the
Declaration of Independence here in New
York, this little square got taken all
to pieces. There had been crowns on the
top of these railings, which were hacked
off. You can still see the marks of the
blows. And the metal statue of King
George the III that had stood in the
middle was pulled down, his head was cut
off, and his body was melted down and
turned into musket balls to be used
against the King's own troops.
>> The toppling of King George's statue
looks like a violent, revolutionary act.
>> [music]
>> But this isn't the image of 1776 the
founding fathers wanted [music] us to
remember.
In 1817, the US Congress commissioned
John Trumbull's painting The Declaration
of Independence. [music]
It hangs in the nation's Capitol
Building in Washington, D.C.
It shows Thomas Jefferson presenting the
draft of the declaration to Congress in
Philadelphia.
At the moment of its birth, the new
nation was at all-out war with the
British Empire.
But history paints the founding of the
United States as a calm, formal scene
speaking of harmony and high ideals.
The Declaration of Independence was
signed in this room.
It explains why America is fighting its
war, why it wants to be independent, how
it's going to form itself into a nation.
It's quite a practical document for the
short term. It explains how things are
going to unfold. But the values it
presents for the long term
have turned it into almost a sacred
text.
>> [music]
>> What makes us exceptional, what makes us
American, is our allegiance to an idea
articulated in a declaration made more
than two centuries ago.
>> We hold these truths to be self-evident
[music]
that all men are created equal.
>> That they are endowed by their creator
>> with certain inalienable rights. Among
these are life,
liberty,
>> and the pursuit of happiness.
>> The Declaration of Independence has gone
down in history as a unanimous statement
of the beliefs of a new nation.
But the writing of the Declaration
exposed a series of highly charged
disagreements.
The document [music] had to satisfy the
demands of people from 13 states with
opposing views on divisive subjects like
religion and slavery.
Professor Danielle Allen has studied the
drafts of the Declaration line by line.
>> So the first draft had an incredible
paragraph condemning King George for a
slave trade that was violating, in the
language of the draft, the sacred rights
of life and liberty of a distant people
in Africa.
And that was cut out by Congress. That
was a pro-slavery moment where it was
too much to say explicitly that Africans
had the same rights of life and liberty
as everybody else. But then we get the
anti-slavery moment, which is in the
phrase life, liberty, and the pursuit of
happiness. So the the tradition of
thinking about rights and the law of
nature that emerged in the 17th and 18th
century often invoked the idea that what
government should do is defend life,
liberty, and property. In the American
context, the concept of property had
become closely connected to a defense of
slavery. So there was a debate between
the happiness concept and the property
concept. The happiness concept won. It's
a compromise concept because the people
who were against slavery could see it as
eroding the justification for slavery.
The people who were in favor of slavery
could think, "Yes, my enslaved people
make me happy." So they they too had a
way of seeing themselves in the
document.
>> Do you think
that this is really a very clever
document indeed because everybody can
look at it and see what they want to
see. It's It's a beautiful compromise.
>> Well, we've forgotten these days, but
one of the core elements of democracy is
compromise.
Which is interesting because often in
the US we like to think, "Oh, what was
the original intent of the founders? And
the fact is there isn't a single answer
to that because they had these moments
of choice. They picked an action. They
agreed on the action but for different
reasons.
>> Even the Declaration's most memorable
statement, that all men are created
equal, was open to interpretation.
>> Did the fact that everybody was equal in
the basic sense of their well-being
mattering mean that everybody should
participate in political power?
The answer to that question for them was
no. John Adams writes to his wife
Abigail when she says, what about the
ladies? Where are they in this? He
writes to her and says, yes, your
well-being, your life, liberty, and
happiness are a part of this, but we
men, we will be in charge of ensuring
that the government succeeds in
delivering that. It was
>> [music]
>> white men with property who were going
to control power.
>> Every 4th of July, the Declaration of
Independence is celebrated as the birth
of the United States.
But it wasn't the end of the war.
America still had to beat the British on
the battlefield.
But the Americans didn't have enough
arms and ammunition to win a war by
themselves.
So to get rid of one king, they turned
for help to another.
King Louis the 16th of France.
Within a week of signing the Declaration
of Independence, the American
revolutionaries sent a copy to the
French monarch.
The British were France's greatest
enemy.
In 1756,
Britain and France had gone to war over
territories in North America. This
became known as the Seven Years' War.
It was a battle for imperial supremacy,
but the British
came out on top.
And the French weren't happy about it.
France lost all of its Canadian colonies
to Britain, as well as parts of the
Caribbean.
And all they had to show for their
efforts was crippling debt.
Imperial France saw the American War of
Independence [music] as the chance to
get its revenge.
In 1776,
>> [music]
>> it began smuggling arms to support the
Patriot cause.
Then in 1778, the French joined the
United States as official allies.
>> The main thing that changed was the
introduction of the French Navy into the
force. [music] The British were were
always dependent upon their navy to keep
themselves supplied from London, to move
troops uh around from place to place,
and with the French Navy now on American
shores,
all of that was cut off. Britannia no
longer ruled the waves. And for them, it
changed the completely the nature of the
war.
>> Do you think that America could have won
without this help from France?
>> No, absolutely not. America could never
have won the war without France.
>> This is not the story of the plucky
little Americans with their muskets and
their plows going out and having a go
against the mighty evil British, is it?
>> And it never was true, and it was never
a good fit. Um
the Americans uh could never have uh
brought themselves up by their own
bootstraps. In fact, the real story
of the American Revolution is that the
United States became the centerpiece of
an international coalition,
which together fought to achieve a
common purpose, to defeat a common
adversary. [music]
>> The last major land battle of the
Revolutionary War was in 1781.
In Yorktown, Virginia, the British
surrendered to George Washington's army
of American and French troops.
But the decisive role of Imperial France
in the American victory was very quickly
played down.
The war was over.
Yet the battle to control the story of
the revolution was just getting started.
>> [music]
>> The early histories of the revolution
told the story almost as a morality tale
with good triumphing.
And that's because the new nation was
still finding its [music] feet. It
needed stability and purpose.
Meanwhile, the French, well, they were
now having a violent revolution of their
own.
They were busy chopping each other's
heads off.
>> [music]
>> Emerson wrote his Concord Hymn in 1837.
By this time, Americans saw themselves
as triumphant underdogs.
His embattled farmers were celebrated in
poetry set to the tune of an old psalm.
>> [singing]
>> The revolution was becoming remembered
as a sacred story outlining America's
God-given destiny to lead others towards
liberty.
>> [singing]
>> In the 1840s, its conquest of Mexican
and Native American territory was
presented as the divine destiny of an
exceptional nation.
>> The idea that um we controlled our own
destiny did not fit very well with the
idea that we depended upon European
powers to support um our uh our birth.
And so, that part of the story became
left out over time.
>> [singing]
>> In the first half of the 19th century,
the nation's patriotism was growing ever
stronger. People were eager to tell
stories of America's revolutionary
heroes.
>> And if they don't exist, then why not
make them up?
>> [music]
>> Take the story of a woman named Molly
Pitcher.
Legend has it that Molly wandered the
field at the Battle of Monmouth in 1778,
bringing water to her husband and his
fellow soldiers.
>> [music]
>> Suddenly,
Molly's husband is shot in the head. He
falls to the ground. She drops her pail
of water, and she cries out, "Lie there,
my darling. I will avenge thee."
Molly Pitcher bravely takes up her
husband's position at the cannon and
battles on.
The next morning, George Washington
himself gives Molly a piece of gold and
assures her that her services will not
be forgotten.
But, in some versions of the story,
George Washington also makes her a
sergeant. And in others, the husband
isn't killed.
He's only injured. And in yet others,
it's not a bucket that Molly is carrying
around the battlefield, it's a pitcher.
And the thirsty soldiers shout out, "Oi,
Molly, we're thirsty. Bring your
pitcher, Molly Pitcher, Molly Pitcher."
Molly is an appealing heroine,
and her battle-scarred 19th-century
image still appears in 21st-century
schoolbooks.
But Molly Pitcher is a fib.
You'll find lots of books about her, but
there are no first-hand accounts that
place her at the Battle of Monmouth.
She's probably an amalgamation of
several brave patriot women.
Some people think that she's Margaret
Corbin, a woman wounded in battle at
Fort Washington who received a war
pension.
Others claim she's Mary Hayes McCauley.
Mary even has a memorial claiming her as
the original Molly Pitcher.
>> [music]
>> But Molly's legend sprung up in the
1830s and 40s when the people who'd
lived through the revolution were dying
out.
Historians started collecting anecdotes
second-hand, and historical accuracy was
often sacrificed in favor of a good
story.
>> Fire!
>> The Liberty Bell is another late arrival
in the story of the birth of the United
States.
The bell used to hang [music] in the
tower above Independence Hall where the
Declaration of Independence was signed.
It was put [music] up in 1753
to call politicians to meetings and to
alert the public to important
announcements.
>> When the Declaration of Independence was
first read in public
and the Liberty Bell was sounded in
celebration,
a witness said it rang as if it meant
something.
In our time, it means something still.
>> But, the Liberty Bell's starring role in
the American Revolution, only entered
the story 71 years after the Declaration
of Independence was signed.
In the 1840s, George Lippard was the
best-selling author in America.
Lippard was best known for his
sensationalist gothic tales filled with
gory murders and [music] vice.
But in 1847, he turned his hand to
historical fiction.
Lippard wrote a story that was set on
the 4th of July, 1776.
He introduces the character of an old
man in humble attire, but he still has a
gleam in his eye. He's the kindly bell
ringer who's in charge at the Liberty
Bell.
And then, there's a young boy with
flaxen hair and laughing eyes of summer
blue.
The story goes that the blue-eyed boy
had the job of signaling to the old man
to ring the bell when the men below
declared independence.
And what a super exciting moment it is.
The little boy, swelling his little
chest, raised himself on tiptoe and
shouted a single word, "Ring!"
Now, the old man is young again. His
veins are filled with new life. Backward
and forward with sturdy strokes, he
swings the tongue. The bell speaks out.
Everybody goes absolutely wild.
The bell speaks to the city and to the
world.
It's a great story. Hmm.
It's the Hollywood version of the 4th of
July before Hollywood even exists. But
it's also entirely made up.
It sounds like heresy, but there's no
evidence at all that the Liberty Bell
was rung on the 4th of July, 1776.
On July the 8th, some of the city bells
were rung to announce the public reading
of the Declaration.
But the steeple of the old State House
was in disrepair, so it's unlikely that
old Liberty was ever rung that week.
But you can't keep a good story down.
Five years later, a significant
historian called Benson Lossing
published his Pictorial Field Book of
the American Revolution, and he, too,
included the blue-eyed boy giving the
signal to ring the bell.
Two years after that, and a biography of
George Washington is published, complete
with the bright-eyed boy.
So, in less than a decade, Lippard's
historical fiction has become accepted
as historical fact.
Thanks to Lippard, the Liberty Bell has
become a central part of the American
story.
The body of Abraham Lincoln was brought
to Philadelphia to lie in state next to
the Liberty Bell after his assassination
in 1865.
In 1917, its image helps to raise $21
billion for the US war effort.
>> Thank you all.
>> And its legend has continued into the
[music] 21st century.
>> And each of the founders coming here
would know the ring of the Liberty Bell.
It rang to announce the first public
reading of the Declaration of
Independence.
>> But in the late 19th century, a new
symbol of the Revolution was forged,
and it would eclipse even the Liberty
Bell in the national consciousness.
>> [music]
>> The Statue of Liberty is a symbol of the
American Revolution at its biggest and
boldest.
Liberty, the central idea from the
Declaration of Independence, was
reimagined as a 300-ft goddess.
Armed with a guiding light and a tablet
bearing the revolutionary date, July the
4th, 1776.
>> But her meaning has never been set in
stone. She's come to represent all kinds
of different things. The revolutionary
alliance with France.
America enlightening the rest of the
world.
And a nation that welcomes immigrants.
Each of these things though comes with
its own little fibs.
>> The Statue of Liberty was a gift from
the French to celebrate their almost
forgotten alliance in the American
Revolution.
But this wasn't a gift from the French
government.
It was a message to it to guard against
tyranny.
The Frenchman who proposed the statue,
Edouard de Laboulaye, was worried about
the lack of democracy in his own
country.
He wanted a statue to honor the United
States as an example of a successful
republic.
But this great American symbol wasn't
originally designed for the United
States.
The sculptor, Frédéric Auguste
Bartholdi, had been planning to build a
similar statue for Egypt.
>> He traveled to Egypt and he showed his
designs of a gigantic figure of a woman
to stand at the entrance to the Suez
Canal. And she was to be veiled in the
Egyptian fashion. She was to hold high a
lantern and she was to
represent Egypt carrying the light of
progress to Asia. And this idea excited
the Egyptians initially, but the expense
was so high and they were expected to
pay for it, they turned it down. So, he
just redesigned it so it would be a
European figure. It would be a
a Roman goddess instead and that it
would represent freedom and not
progress.
>> The Statue of Liberty was unveiled in
1886.
But to some, a statue celebrating the
ideal of liberty was misleading.
Women protested at the unveiling
ceremony.
She might be Lady Liberty, but she still
couldn't vote.
While African-Americans pointed [music]
out that liberty and equality still
weren't realities for them.
Soon a new meaning for the Statue of
Liberty emerged.
During fundraising to build the statue,
a well-known Jewish poet called Emma
Lazarus [music]
had written a poem to raise money.
Lazarus
>> [music]
>> was an advocate for refugees and her
poem gave Lady Liberty a new political
message.
>> Lazarus' poem was called The New
Colossus.
In it, she showed Lady Liberty almost
standing on the doorstep of America,
welcoming people in.
The line that everybody remembers goes,
"Give me your tired, your poor,
your huddled masses
yearning to breathe free."
>> Nearly 20 years after the opening,
Lazarus' friends had a verse from that
poem engraved on a plaque at the base of
the statue.
And now the poem was all the more
resonant. In 1892,
an immigration center had opened on
neighboring Ellis Island.
Lady Liberty would now be forever
[music] connected with the idea of the
United States welcoming immigrants from
all over the world.
>> Do you think that the key to her success
in becoming the symbol of America is the
fact that she's so flexible? She can
mean almost anything to anybody, can't
she?
>> Yeah, scholars have called her a hollow
icon. And that means that because she's
really empty inside, uh she can be
filled with anyone's notion of what
liberty means to them. That did
transform her into having all kinds of
new meanings, like uh symbol for
immigrants, a symbol for for American
nationalism, a symbol for all sorts of
ideas.
>> What started out as a powerful symbol of
the French alliance in the war of
independence had been overtaken by
another story.
But in the 20th century, there would be
new opportunities for the story of the
revolution to shape the American
landscape.
Jazz Age New York was the era of the
skyscraper, an emblem of a country
looking to the future.
But at the same time, American
architecture was also looking to the
past.
Churches, post offices, schools were
being built in a style known as colonial
revival.
George Washington High School was built
in 1925, just 5 years before the
Chrysler Building opened.
The name of the school refers to the
American Revolution, and so too does its
design. That red brick and those white
columns, especially the bell tower on
top, they all remind me of Independence
Hall in Philadelphia or some of the 18th
century buildings of Boston.
>> [music]
>> Now, anybody could live in a home or eat
in a diner that looked like 1770s
America.
>> [music]
>> The Colonial Revival was pitched as a
truly American style.
You were supposed to look at it and
somehow feel the special qualities of
the founding fathers, their courage or
maybe their virtue.
It was used for public buildings to show
people how to be American. In fact,
architecture could be a way to make
America great again.
>> [music]
>> But this is an idealized version of the
revolutionary era. It comes complete
with heroic founding fathers who embody
the declaration's high ideals of liberty
and equality.
And it's another distortion of the
truth.
In the heart of Philadelphia, next to
Independence Hall, is the site of the
President's House. Long before the White
House as we know it existed, George
Washington, as president, lived here.
But the house that existed on this site
has a darker side to its story. Because
the unpalatable truth is that Washington
was a slave owner.
At the time of his death in 1799,
there were over 300 slaves working on
Washington's Virginia plantation.
Nine slaves worked for him here [music]
in Philadelphia.
When the foundations of the president's
house were discovered in the year 2000,
>> [music]
>> a campaign started to have Washington's
Philadelphia slaves remembered at the
site.
Now their names are carved [music] in
stone here and their story is recorded,
but only after an 8-year battle fought
by activists like Michael Coard.
>> Why do some Americans and some very
powerful Americans not want to think of
Washington as a slave owner?
>> It shakes the very foundation of
American history. If there were ever a
man-god
in American history, it's George
Washington. George Washington is the
foundation of what America represents.
So, if you find out that at the very
core, at the very foundation, this man
had such a horrific blemish, that
blemish being slavery, people don't want
to admit the truth. If he's flawed, then
America's flawed.
>> How did George Washington treat his
slaves?
>> Well, any person who enslaves any other
person automatically treats them bad by
enslaving them. That's the first thing.
But even beyond that, George Washington
was a miserable miser when it came to
his enslaved population. He was
notorious for having them run around in
rags, having them hungry, having them
emaciated. In 1780, there was something
called the Pennsylvania Gradual
Abolition Act. They passed a law saying,
"Hey, if you bring enslaved human beings
into this state and you hold them for
six straight months, at the end of that
6-month period, they can petition for
their freedom."
>> Yes.
>> So, what George Washington would do is
wait for 5 months, 29 days, take them
across state lines, and then bring them
back. Now, people say, "Well, yeah, he
kind of skirted the law." No, he didn't
just skirt the law, he broke the law.
>> Nobody wants to hear that about our
great hero, George Washington, do they?
Oh my goodness.
>> And you know, it's so funny because if
you want to say George Washington was a
great general, you can say that. If you
want to say George Washington was a
great president, you can say that. But,
can you be a great human being when you
hold 316 fellow human beings in brutal
bondage and play the type of games he
did with Pennsylvania's gradual
abolition act?
>> Why is it important to tell this story
about George Washington, slave owner?
>> It's important in order for America and
ultimately the world to be able to move
toward racial healing. We might not ever
reach that Kumbaya moment where we all
come together as a human species, but at
least we can begin to respect one
another. And you respect people when you
find out where they came from, what
they're about. In order to reach the
truth, you have to tell the truth, and
you have to tell the truth at the
beginning. The beginning of American
political history is George Washington.
You got to tell the truth, the whole
truth, and nothing but the truth.
>> In the 21st century, a battle still
rages to decide whose version of history
gets told.
>> [music]
>> And in 2015, that story stepped on stage
on Broadway.
Hamilton is a groundbreaking retelling
of the birth of the United States as a
hip-hop musical.
Created by Lin-Manuel Miranda, it's
based on the life [music] of founding
father Alexander Hamilton.
George Washington's right-hand man on
the battlefield and Treasury Secretary
in his cabinet. [music]
It's been praised by critics and
presidents, won 11 Tony Awards, a
Grammy, and a Pulitzer Prize.
>> To its fans, the musical Hamilton is a
revolution in itself. It tells the story
of the American Revolution, but all the
historical characters are played by
actors of color. The only white one
plays poor old King George III.
So, the stage is full of
African-Americans, Puerto Ricans, and
Chinese-Americans.
There's a big sign on the front of the
theater, and it says, "History is
happening here in Manhattan."
>> [music]
>> Hamilton's racial diversity has made the
story of the Founding Fathers more
accessible for modern Americans.
But historian Lyra Monteiro believes
that this masks the inequalities at the
heart of a revolution fought for liberty
and equality.
>> I I saw the show the week it opened on
Broadway, and I was blown away by, you
know, the quality of it as a work of
art, but immediately I was like, "Wait a
second, this is not
it's not cool that these guys are so
cool,
right? By
turning the Founding Fathers into these,
you know, interesting, cool, clever,
exciting, you know, relatable guys,
right? In suggesting that they're just
the same as, you know, African-Americans
who were raised in the projects, it ends
up obscuring really how much that found
it that founding moment was about the
oppression of everyone who wasn't a
white man. It was not a revolution for
everybody.
>> These are definitely people who did not
uh want the ancestors of the performers
on stage
to count as citizens in the nation they
created.
>> Do you think it's possible that there
could be a generation of school kids who
go away thinking that all of the
founding fathers were great guys just
like Obama.
>> Yeah, I think there's a real possibility
of that. And I think there's a real
problem with that, too, though, because
it continues to perpetuate this idea
that in order to have a rightful claim
to power in this country, a rightful
claim to be in this country, you have to
show that you have a that you have a
claim to the the the country's past,
right? And so, black men and Latino men
representing the founders is a way of
saying, "Look, we belong here, too.
We're as We're as American as white
people."
And I think that's kind of shitty. I
don't think that we should have to, you
know, look back to that always in order
to make a claim that we belong, because
ultimately we're still leaving other
people out.
>> But isn't it just a musical? How much
does it matter?
>> Sure, it's just a musical, but it's a
musical about a very,
um,
intensely symbolic moment in American
history that has an impact on how
Americans understand ourselves.
>> At the center of the story [music] of
Hamilton is a line, "Who lives, who
dies, who tells your story?"
>> [music]
>> This show is explicitly asking questions
about who gets to write [music] history.
Who controls the narrative of the
founding [music] era?
And in a story where some of American
history's biggest [music] fibs abound,
this can surely only be a good thing.
The history of the American Revolution
has been mythologized, distorted,
reimagined, and sometimes just made up.
And that's partly because it's such an
inspiring moment in time.
>> America has such a powerful national
mythology. It makes Americans feel good
about their country, and it's how their
country presents itself to the world.
But if history teaches us anything at
all, it's that we have to ask questions.
Who is telling us the story?
How are they spinning it?
And could they be telling us fibs?
>> Next time, the American Civil War.
>> You are darling, darling.
>> Was Abraham Lincoln really fighting to
end slavery?
>> Lincoln [music] always did what was in
the best interest of his race.
>> I'll uncover the fibs in the story of a
conflict that continues to divide the
United States.
>> [music]